[Host] Welcome to Japanese Daily News. I'm Maya. Today is August fourth. Automaker Nissan is back in the black for the first time in two years, after deep cost cuts — but its road ahead is still rough. Let's listen.
[News] 今日のニュースです。
[News] 自動車メーカーの日産自動車は3日、今年4月から6月までの3か月間の決算を発表しました。
[News] 決算の説明会は、横浜市にある日産のグローバル本社で開かれました。
[News] 最終的な利益は37億円の黒字で、2年ぶりの黒字転換となりました。
[News] 日産はこれまで、販売の不振などで赤字が続き、厳しい経営の状態でした。
[News] 売り上げは2兆9600億円あまりで、去年の同じ時期より9.5%増えました。
[News] 本業のもうけを示す営業利益も、778億円の黒字となりました。
[News] 黒字になった大きな理由は、工場を減らすなどの「構造改革」で、コストを大きく下げたことです。
[News] また、アメリカの関税の負担が軽くなったことや、円安も、利益を押し上げました。
[News] 世界全体での販売台数は、70万1000台でした。
[News] 中国では、電気自動車などの「新エネルギー車」の販売が好調で、去年の同じ時期より7.2%増えました。
[News] 日本でも、新型の「キックス」が人気を集め、販売は1.3%増えました。
[News] 一方、日産は、今年度の世界での販売台数の見通しを、15万台引き下げました。
[News] 中国での需要の減少や、中東情勢の混乱を見込んでいるためです。
[News] 2年ぶりの黒字となりましたが、通期の見通しは厳しく、経営の立て直しは、これからも続きます。
[Host] Now let's break it down, sentence by sentence.
[Slow] 自動車メーカーの日産自動車は3日、今年4月から6月までの3か月間の決算を発表しました。
[Host] Automaker Nissan announced its financial results for the three months from April to June on the third.
[Vocab] 決算
[Host] It means financial results — a company's report of profit and loss.
[Slow] 最終的な利益は37億円の黒字で、2年ぶりの黒字転換となりました。
[Host] The bottom-line profit was three point seven billion yen — the first return to the black in two years.
[Vocab] 黒字
[Host] It means a surplus — being in the black, the opposite of a deficit.
[Slow] 日産はこれまで、販売の不振などで赤字が続き、厳しい経営の状態でした。
[Host] Until now, weak sales had kept the company in the red, in a tough business condition.
[Vocab] 不振
[Host] It means a slump — when sales or performance are weak.
[Slow] 売り上げは2兆9600億円あまりで、去年の同じ時期より9.5%増えました。
[Host] Revenue was just over two point nine six trillion yen, up nine point five percent from a year earlier.
[Vocab] 売り上げ
[Host] It means sales, or revenue.
[Slow] 黒字になった大きな理由は、工場を減らすなどの「構造改革」で、コストを大きく下げたことです。
[Host] The main reason for the profit was structural reform, such as cutting factories, which sharply lowered costs.
[Vocab] 構造改革
[Host] It means structural reform — rebuilding how a company works.
[Slow] また、アメリカの関税の負担が軽くなったことや、円安も、利益を押し上げました。
[Host] A lighter burden from American tariffs and the weak yen also pushed profits up.
[Vocab] 関税
[Host] It means tariff — a tax on imported goods.
[Slow] 中国では、電気自動車などの「新エネルギー車」の販売が好調で、去年の同じ時期より7.2%増えました。
[Host] In China, sales of new energy vehicles such as electric cars were strong, up seven point two percent.
[Vocab] 好調
[Host] It means doing well — in good shape.
[Slow] 一方、日産は、今年度の世界での販売台数の見通しを、15万台引き下げました。
[Host] On the other hand, Nissan cut its global sales forecast for this fiscal year by one hundred fifty thousand vehicles.
[Vocab] 見通し
[Host] It means outlook, or forecast.
[Slow] 中国での需要の減少や、中東情勢の混乱を見込んでいるためです。
[Host] That is because it expects weaker demand in China and turmoil in the Middle East.
[Vocab] 需要
[Host] It means demand.
[Slow] 2年ぶりの黒字となりましたが、通期の見通しは厳しく、経営の立て直しは、これからも続きます。
[Host] Despite the return to profit, the full-year outlook is severe, and the company's rebuilding continues.
[Vocab] 立て直し
[Host] It means rebuilding — getting back on track.
[Host] Let's listen to the whole story one more time.
[News] 自動車メーカーの日産自動車は3日、今年4月から6月までの3か月間の決算を発表しました。
[News] 決算の説明会は、横浜市にある日産のグローバル本社で開かれました。
[News] 最終的な利益は37億円の黒字で、2年ぶりの黒字転換となりました。
[News] 日産はこれまで、販売の不振などで赤字が続き、厳しい経営の状態でした。
[News] 売り上げは2兆9600億円あまりで、去年の同じ時期より9.5%増えました。
[News] 本業のもうけを示す営業利益も、778億円の黒字となりました。
[News] 黒字になった大きな理由は、工場を減らすなどの「構造改革」で、コストを大きく下げたことです。
[News] また、アメリカの関税の負担が軽くなったことや、円安も、利益を押し上げました。
[News] 世界全体での販売台数は、70万1000台でした。
[News] 中国では、電気自動車などの「新エネルギー車」の販売が好調で、去年の同じ時期より7.2%増えました。
[News] 日本でも、新型の「キックス」が人気を集め、販売は1.3%増えました。
[News] 一方、日産は、今年度の世界での販売台数の見通しを、15万台引き下げました。
[News] 中国での需要の減少や、中東情勢の混乱を見込んでいるためです。
[News] 2年ぶりの黒字となりましたが、通期の見通しは厳しく、経営の立て直しは、これからも続きます。
[Host] Time for a short quiz. Listen and try to answer.
[Slow] 日産自動車の最終的な利益は、何億円の黒字でしたか。
[Host] Three point seven billion yen.
[Slow] 黒字になったのは、何年ぶりですか。
[Host] Two years — the first profit in two years.
[Slow] 日産は、今年度の販売台数の見通しを、何万台引き下げましたか。
[Host] One hundred fifty thousand vehicles, because of weaker demand in China and turmoil in the Middle East.
[Host] That's all for today. Nissan climbed out of the red for the first time in two years, but its recovery is far from finished. See you tomorrow.
[News] また明日。